Emanuele Rossi

 ♦ Barcelona
 ■ emanuele.rossi1909@gmail.com
 ♦ emanuelerossi.co.uk
 in emanuele-rossi
 ♠ emanuelerossi.co.uk

Summary

I'm an ML researcher specializing in generative models for structural biology. Before jumping into MLxBio, my background combined **fundamental research** experience with real-world **product impact**. I'm the first author of Scalable Inception Graph Network , now **used in production by AirBnB**, and Temporal Graph Network , which has received over **750 Github stars**. While at Twitter, I successfully developed multiple ML models for the "who-to-follow" recommendation feature, resulting in an increase of over **1.2M follow actions daily**.

Education

Imperial College London

Oct 2020 - Feb 2024

Ph.D. in Computer Science - Supervisor: Prof. Michael Bronstein

- ∘ My research ∠ focused on solving the challenges preventing the success of **Graph Neural Networks** on real-world applications
- My work has been published at top conferences including ICML, ICLR, AAAI and RecSys

University of Cambridge

Oct 2018 - Jun 2019

Master in Advanced Computer Science – Supervisor: Prof. Pietro Liò

- Graduated with **Distinction** (4.0 GPA)
- ∘ Thesis: "Graph Deep Learning for ncRNA data" (published 🗹 at KDD 2019 GDL workshop)

Imperial College London

Oct 2015 - Jun 2018

Bachelor in Computer Science

o Graduated with First Class Honors (4.0 GPA)

Experience

Machine Learning Researcher

NYC (remote)

VantAI

Jan 2024 - Present

- Leading the development of an all-atom foundation model for structural biology, leveraging Latent Diffusion to perform multiple tasks simultaneously, including cofolding, design, inverse folding, and docking
- Data processing: Curated and structured biomolecular datasets for efficient and de-leaked model training (see Plinder ☑ and Pinder ☑)
- Model formulation & exploration: Designed and refined diffusion-based formulations and model architectures
- Inference & benchmarking: Built a robust inference pipeline and developed comprehensive evaluation metrics

Machine Learning Researcher

London

Twitter

Jun 2019 - Feb 2023

- Worked on applied and fundamental research around graph neural networks
- $\circ\,$ Scaled these technologies to graphs with tens of billions of edges
- Developed an embedding-based model to recommend users "who to follow", leading to an **increase of more** than 1M follow actions per day on the platform

Machine Learning Engineer

London

Fabula AI Mar 2019 - Jun 2019

- Researched and developed novel graph deep learning models for fake news classification
- Fabula AI was acquired by Twitter in June 2019

Software Engineering Intern

Google

California Jul 2017 – Oct 2017

• Worked in the Google Play Store infrastructure team

Selected Publications

- o E. Rossi et al. Temporal Graph Networks for Deep Learning on Dynamic Graphs. ICML 2020 GRL Workshop. arXiv:2006.10637 ₺, blog ₺. A new model for deep learning on dynamic graphs (¿300 citations, ¿700 Github stars). Adopted by memgraph ₺ (graph analytics company) and used by GraphCore to benchmark their hardware ₺.
- ∘ E. Rosst*, F. Frasca* et al. SIGN: Scalable Inception Graph Neural Networks. ICML 2020 GRL Workshop. arXiv:2004.11198 ₺, blog ₺. First graph deep learning model to scale to graphs with billions of edges (¿200 citations). Used in production by Airbnb ₺.
- ∘ B. Chamberlain, S. Shirobokov, E. Rossi et al. Graph Neural Networks for Link Prediction with Subgraph Sketching. ICLR 2022, Oral (top 5%). arXiv:2209.15486 ☑. First GNN model to scale link prediction to graphs with millions of nodes thanks to sketching, a hashing technique which enables efficient computation of subgraph statistics.
- o E. Rossi et al. On the Unreasonable Effectiveness of Feature propagation in Learning on Graphs with Missing Node Features. Learning on Graphs Conference 2022. arXiv:2111.12128 ☑, blog ☑. First model to enable scalable graph learning with partially missing node features.

Projects and Awards

LeadTheFuture

Jun 2018 - Mar 2023

Co-Founder

- LeadTheFuture Z is a non-profit mentoring organization and the largest merit-based STEM community in Italy, with more than 200 mentors (engineers, researchers, and entrepreneurs) and 500 selected mentees
- Our work has been featured in Forbes 🗹

Talks and Blog Posts

∘ I have written a series of blog posts on my research (full list 🗹) and have been invited to give over 10 talks (full list 🖒)